<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hunting of the pox a pleasant discourse betweene the authour, and pild-garlicke : wherein is declared the nature of the dissease, how it came, and how it may bee cured / by J. T. Westminster.</title>
            <author>J. T., of Westminster.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13316</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23624.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1011</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23173099</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23173099</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26340</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13316)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26340)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1782:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hunting of the pox a pleasant discourse betweene the authour, and pild-garlicke : wherein is declared the nature of the dissease, how it came, and how it may bee cured / by J. T. Westminster.</title>
                  <author>J. T., of Westminster.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[21] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.W. for I.T. and are to be sold by Philip Birch at the signe of the Bible neere Guildhall-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poxvirus diseases --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26340:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HVNTING OF THE POX:</p>
            <p>A PLEASANT <hi>DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe betweene the Authour,</hi> and Pild-Garlicke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is declared the nature of the</hi> Diſſeaſe, how it came, and how it may bee cured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By J. T. Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. W.</hi> for <hi>I. T.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Philip Birch</hi> at the ſigne of the Bible neere <hi>Guildhall</hi>-gate. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26340:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26340:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE PREFACE</hi> to the Reader.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>I</hi> Would not wiſh that any man ſhould here offended be</l>
            <l>With any thing that hee ſhall reade, that written is by me.</l>
            <l>Ne did I thinke at firſt to put in print ſuch idle ſtuffe;</l>
            <l>I writ it for a friend, which did eſteeme it well enough:</l>
            <l>But after when that Copies were waxt common all about,</l>
            <l>And that ſome men vnknowne to me, in Print would ſet it out,</l>
            <l>I thought it beſt begin my ſelfe, ſince that the Booke was mine;</l>
            <l>And now haue brought to this paſſe, it is not mine, but thine:</l>
            <l>And thank <hi>Pild-Garlicke</hi> if thou find ought worth in this ſame Booke,</l>
            <l>Hee was the ſecond man, I thinke, that on the ſame did looke.</l>
            <l>And how we firſt acquainted came, There will ſhew to thee:</l>
            <l>For he made mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge my Booke, by conference had with mee.</l>
            <l>Ne haue I writ this ſilly worke vnto the learned ſort,</l>
            <l>Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the twaine I doe ſubmit my ſelfe to their report.</l>
            <l>Now if ſome Reader finde ſuch fault, himſelfe liſt not to mend;</l>
            <l>Let each mend one, for all haue faults, ſo ſhall we ſooner end.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:26340:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26340:3"/>
            <head>A CONFERENCE BETVVENE THE AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour and <hi>Pild-Garlicke, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Booke called, The</hi> Hunting of the Pox and the <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of the Diſeaſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon an idle day it chaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t</l>
            <l>I walkt to ſee a Play,</l>
            <l>And as I went, I ouertooke</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pild-Garlike</hi> on the way,</l>
            <l>Who all alone a Plimmouth horſe</l>
            <l>went leading in his hand,</l>
            <l>And as a man thats Male-content,</l>
            <l>his Hatt without a band:</l>
            <l>A Sattin Dublet ſomewhat torne, with bootes and bretch vs ſutable,</l>
            <l>He ſeemd a Gentleman, whoſe minde to faſhions was not mutable.</l>
            <l>A falling Band, God dambe me call'd, a Rapi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r by his ſide,</l>
            <l>He ware no Cloke for comelineſſe a Cloake doeth often hide.</l>
            <l>He had of Spaniſh Buttons ſtore vpon his forehead mixt;</l>
            <l>And where that they were falne away, there Stooles in place were fixt.</l>
            <l>This is the man then did I thinke, perhaps hath read my Booke;</l>
            <l>If not, I will perſwade him too, that he thereon will looke.</l>
            <l>God ſaue you Sir, good Sir, ſaid I, make bold to craue your name.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pild-Garlike,</hi> anſwered he, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd, waxe angry at the ſame.</l>
            <l>Nay gentle Sir, I would not wiſh your anger any way,</l>
            <l>I meant but ſpeake a word or two, if you would pleaſe to ſtay.</l>
            <l>Speake what thou wilt, <hi>Pild-Garlike</hi> ſaid, I haue no haſte, quoth he,</l>
            <l>So thou no money matters aske; for that go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s low with me.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:26340:4"/>Why then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir will you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Booke, a very fine Booke indeed,</l>
            <l>And ſuch a Booke perhaps the like you ſcarce ſhall ſeldome reade.</l>
            <l>What is thy Booke, my honeſt friend, is it a Booke of Newes?</l>
            <l>I Sir, and true tranſlated out of French, and new ſent from the Starres.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The Hunting of the Pox,</hi> good Sir, and pleaſant for to reade,</l>
            <l>And if you keepe it all your life, 'twill nere once you nob <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad.</l>
            <l>Ha, ha, thou art a merry Knave, couldſt them perſwade me ſo,</l>
            <l>Thy Newes is new, no, it is ſtale, I read i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> long agoe:</l>
            <l>And two I gaue a Waiting Mayd, to reade on now and than;</l>
            <l>And ſhee did giue her Maſter one, the other to his man:</l>
            <l>And ſo farewell, my honeſt friend, to reade the Pox is coſt,</l>
            <l>Thrice haue I read it all my ſelfe, and glad now it is loſt.</l>
            <l>Nay, ſtay good ſir, If that you pleaſe, and drinke a pince of Wine,</l>
            <l>And I will tell a merry ieſt hope to a friend of mine.</l>
            <l>Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee at <hi>Winch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> the old, where <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> Temple ſtood:</l>
            <l>The Stewes, men ſay, was founded there, and now of late as good</l>
            <l>A Brothell houſe, and to the ſame reſorted this my friend.</l>
            <l>The Matron of the houſe which knew his minde, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o what end</l>
            <l>Hee vſde to haunt her vnchaſte d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes, ſhe counſeld one ſtraightway,</l>
            <l>To feaſt him with a towne-bred Gooſe, if he would pleaſe to ſtay.</l>
            <l>He was content, and offered too his helpe this Gooſe to dreſſe,</l>
            <l>And ſome was bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lde, ſome roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſome boylde, three diſhes to a meſſe.</l>
            <l>Is this a Wincheſter Gooſe, quoth he, when he had fed his fill:</l>
            <l>If ere I feaſt it ſo againe, ſhall be againſt my will.</l>
            <l>The Kitchen was too hote he ſaid, the Cooke-roome doores were bar'd,</l>
            <l>His Gooſe and gyblets ſcal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and burnt, and all the feaſt was mar'd:</l>
            <l>In fine, he tooke his towne-bred Gooſe, as ſhee did giue it him,</l>
            <l>And brought it to a Barbers man, that was both neat and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im:</l>
            <l>A fine young fellow full of skill, and aske him if hee could</l>
            <l>Tell him what vncouth ſhapen thing it was he did behold.</l>
            <l>Well, quoth the Barber, what ſay you? you know beſt what it is;</l>
            <l>As for my part I oft haue ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ene a fayrer beaſt then this.</l>
            <l>A beaſt ſaid he, nay then thou l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt, I ſoe thou haſt no skill,</l>
            <l>I bought it for a towne-bred Gooſe, though now againſt my will,</l>
            <l>As it falles out to my hard hap. Well, quoth the Barber then,</l>
            <l>It is no Fowle in forme nor ſhape, no Gooſe nor Turky-Hen;</l>
            <l>But a plaine French Coulſtaffe you haue goe, where with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou ſore haue fought:</l>
            <l>Your weapon which your ſelfe hath beat, it ſeens your ſelfe had brought.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:26340:4"/>A Coul-ſtaffe ſaid <hi>Pild-Garlike</hi> then, is this the warres in <hi>France</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then haue I had ſome blowes therewith, by fortune, not by chance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Yet haue recouerd well enough, ſo might this friend of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e,</l>
            <l>And ſo I pray thee end this tale, vntill another time;</l>
            <l>For I haue other things to ſpeake, ſince thou haſt made me ſtay,</l>
            <l>Faine would I know this <hi>French-diſeaſe,</hi> which raigneth at this day,</l>
            <l>And which is found in euery Land, how might that firſt beginne,</l>
            <l>For ſure if <hi>Purgatory</hi> be, or penance due for ſinne:</l>
            <l>Then he who doth endure this paine, need feare no other hell,</l>
            <l>He hath enough, who hath the <hi>Pox,</hi> that in his bones doe dwell.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pild-Garlike<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I perceiue you ſpeake, by great experience ſure,</l>
            <l>Doe reade my Booke, and ſee what paines poore <hi>Morbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> did endure,</l>
            <l>For there was euen plaine hell indeed, if hell on earth might bee,</l>
            <l>For light and darkneſſe, heate and cold, did to his paines agree:</l>
            <l>But now to ſatisfie your minde how this Diſeaſe firſt came.</l>
            <l>So farre as Stories make record, Ile doe the beſt I can;</l>
            <l>One thouſand foure hundred ninty three, the <hi>French</hi> with puſant power</l>
            <l>Beſieging <hi>Naples</hi> at that time, till <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth Emperour</l>
            <l>Came there, and brake the ſiege perforce, and in time of his ſtay,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Columbus</hi> to the Emperour did, preſent vpon a day</l>
            <l>A company of <hi>Indians,</hi> which the <hi>Pox</hi> had naturally,</l>
            <l>And they diſperſt it in the campes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Columbus</hi> was an <hi>Italian</hi> borne, and firſt that did diſcouer</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Weſt-India</hi> ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and people there, and brought of one and other</l>
            <l>To ſhew to Chriſtian Princes, what ſtrange Countries they had found,</l>
            <l>What fertill Lands; what fruits, what mines, did in each place abound,</l>
            <l>To moue them for to goe poſſeſſe, ſuch riches offered them,</l>
            <l>Since in thoſe Countries there was none, but naked ſauage men:</l>
            <l>The ſouldiers which that time lay there, did couet for to lye</l>
            <l>With thoſe ſtrange wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which were brought, but what they got therby</l>
            <l>Too many know, to their much griefe; the <hi>French</hi> did put the blame</l>
            <l>Vpon the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that brought it to <hi>Naples</hi> when they came;</l>
            <l>The <hi>Neapolitans</hi> did ſay, the <hi>French</hi> did bring it them,</l>
            <l>For they this painfull ſore diſeaſe, did neuer know till then:</l>
            <l>The <hi>Flammings</hi> call it <hi>Spaniſh Pox,</hi> and ſure they brought it firſt</l>
            <l>To Chriſtendome, as you haue heard, and therefore moſt are cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt:</l>
            <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> likewiſe, when they haue met, ſome part of this Diſeaſe,</l>
            <l>They vſe in ieſt to ſay that they are bit with <hi>Spaniſh Fleas,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:26340:5"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> behinde, as Fleas doe vſe to doe,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, belike they vſe it too.</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſport, and loue know and than,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, is not a Gentleman:</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> withall, the <hi>Pox</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> doth ſtaine and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their clothes, the other foules the bone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they in plaine good troth, will ſweare it came to vs</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and therefore takes the name of <hi>Morbur Gallicus.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pild-Garlike,</hi> now I thinke, I haue full ſatisfied your minde,</l>
            <l>And if you ſearch a thouſand bookes, more truth you ſhall not finde.</l>
            <l>You ſee what poſting off there is, the <hi>Pox</hi> is no mans friend,</l>
            <l>And ſince that none will father it, I heere will make an end.</l>
            <l>Nay, doe not ſo, <hi>Pild-Garlike</hi> ſaid, lets heere a little more</l>
            <l>The <hi>Hunting of the Pox,</hi> which you did ſpeake of firſt before.</l>
            <l>Content, good Syr, and therewithall he made no longer ſtay,</l>
            <l>But tooke his booke, and turn'd the leaſe, and thus began to ſay.</l>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Hunting of the Pox: with the Life and Death of Morbus Gallicus.</head>
               <l>A Young Italian Gentleman, of birth deſcended well,</l>
               <l>Of ſtature comely, faire &amp; proud, as thoſe know him could tell;</l>
               <l>His father died, and hauing got his wealth all in his hands,</l>
               <l>To trauaile now was his deſire, to ſee ſome forraine lands:</l>
               <l>His name <hi>Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Publicus:</hi> and was a <hi>Romane</hi> borne;</l>
               <l>He hated thoſe deſpiſde his name, or Country had in ſcorne.</l>
               <l>To <hi>France</hi> he now his iourney tooke, to ſee the pleaſant ſoile,</l>
               <l>The faſhions there to know and learne, he meant to ſtay a while:</l>
               <l>And finding of the Country ſweet, and women that were faire,</l>
               <l>The ſtore of Vineyards, and of fruits, withall a holeſome ayre:</l>
               <l>Meant there to ſet his ſtaffe, and reſt, and gan acquaintance ſeeke,</l>
               <l>And ſuch acquaintance as himſelfe, he thought could loue and like.</l>
               <l>At length he met a <hi>Curteſan,</hi> an old Dogge at the game,</l>
               <l>Her name was <hi>Veneris,</hi> people ſaid, the Diuell ought him ſhame;</l>
               <l>And made this foole to fall in loue, when firſt he heard her name.</l>
               <l>Shee painted was, both face and breſts, and hands with azure veines,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:5"/>And for to ſet her fleſh to ſale, ſhee ſparde no skill nor paines:</l>
               <l>He thought an Angell he had met, when firſt he ſaw her face,</l>
               <l>So mayden-like behaued her ſelfe in geſture and in pace,</l>
               <l>With words ſo fitting to his minde, ſet out with comely grace:</l>
               <l>Yet had the <hi>Pox</hi> ſo bither bones, and Hounds which on her tended,</l>
               <l>Fell on at length <hi>Saperbus</hi> fleſh, till that his life they ended.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eris,</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hound moſt faire, by Arte and Nature made,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Neapolitan</hi> by birth, a <hi>Curteſan</hi> by trade:</l>
               <l>Her Syer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Dog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>India</hi> breed, her Dam in ſtewes brought vp,</l>
               <l>And ſhee her ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into <hi>France,</hi> where quickly ſhee was put</l>
               <l>Into an honeſt Brothel-houſe, for that muſt be the name,</l>
               <l>Therefor to learne, and be brought vp, till ſhee be paſt all ſhame.</l>
               <l>Shee was the firſt that ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de vpon <hi>Superbus</hi> in his ſport,</l>
               <l>And made him poore and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, God knowes as men of him report;</l>
               <l>And altered all his body cleane, that ſtrangers where he came</l>
               <l>Did call him <hi>Morbus Gallicus,</hi> or French-diſeaſed man:</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Morbus</hi> was not then his name, but ſhee did giue it him,</l>
               <l>And for becauſe he would be knowne, to be one of her kin,</l>
               <l>Shee left a token and a marke, that ſtucke faſt to his skin.</l>
               <l>At length this Hound, with all her Whelpes, he entertain'd at laſt,</l>
               <l>Though in the end he would haue run, away from them full faſt:</l>
               <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch like <hi>Actr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> whom his Hounds, their Maſter eate vnknowne,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he like a Hart with hornes, and haire was ouergrowne,</l>
               <l>And yet the Huntſman knew full well the Hounds were all his owne,</l>
               <l>And would haue ſpoke, if that he could, and calde each by his name,</l>
               <l>Whereby they ſhould haue ceaſt to bite, if Dogges had any ſhame.</l>
               <l>But theſe Dogges; which I tend to ſpeake, was of another kinde;</l>
               <l>Of other nature and of forme, and of another minde:</l>
               <l>For firſt they caught <hi>Superbus</hi> purſe, and eate the bottome out,</l>
               <l>Then on his gay and ſilken clothes, and lapt him in a clout.</l>
               <l>And thus in paſſing by degrees, they thought beſt to begin</l>
               <l>To ſtrippe him firſt, and ſo they might come better to his skin.</l>
               <l>Thus was <hi>Superbus Publican</hi> ſo lapt and wrapt with ſhame;</l>
               <l>That he was malecontent, perforce to leaue his publike name.</l>
               <l>Not one good part was in theſe Hounds, though he his wealth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaue,</l>
               <l>Saue that they ſhewde their loue in this, they brought him to his graue.</l>
               <l>It reſteth now to ſpeake in briefe, the ſtorie as I finde,</l>
               <l>The hunting with the Hounds, their names, and natures of their kinde:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:6"/>That each good man that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, may draw his ſword at them,</l>
               <l>And ſtolne no do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe to kill ſuch beaſts as would kill men.</l>
               <l>Now after <hi>Veneris</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Morbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to the quicke,</l>
               <l>And like a Horſe-l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, and to his downe did ſticke,</l>
               <l>That he was faine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y againe, much like a new faine Deere,</l>
               <l>Which when the other Dogges and Hounds did ſent and ouer-heare,</l>
               <l>The Kennell all ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in at once, more then a man would thinke,</l>
               <l>Whoſe breathes like Carrin did infect the ayre with lothſome ſtinke:</l>
               <l>There was no ſounding of retreate by winding horne was heard,</l>
               <l>For euery Dogge ran for his part, as if he had been ſtaru'd.</l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ra,</hi> that alwaies ſtill in running had delight,</l>
               <l>Did ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon his raynes and backe, and there did gnaw and bight;</l>
               <l>This <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ra</hi> an olde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eade Hound, ſome ſay in <hi>Sodom</hi> bred,</l>
               <l>Would neuer leaue, if that ſhee might, vntill her prey were dead.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>bo,</hi> with her ſtealing pace vpon his groyne did faſt,</l>
               <l>And if ſhee ſuffered might haue been, would eate his guts at laſt.</l>
               <l>This <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>bo</hi> had to Sire a Curre, from <hi>Portugals</hi> he came,</l>
               <l>A Curteſan in <hi>Lisbone</hi> Towne, was ſaid to be her Damme:</l>
               <l>Shee had of Puppyes two or three, <hi>Amorous</hi> ſome them call,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that like to Mulberies, vpon the skinne doe fall,</l>
               <l>Theſe ſeazde vpon the <hi>Virgo</hi> top, and ſtucke faſt to his skinne,</l>
               <l>Which growing ripe and turnde to ſeed, like warts they doe beginne.</l>
               <l>Then came <hi>Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>cula,</hi> a Brache, her Dam and Sier of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A wicked Whelpe it was, and put poore <hi>Morbus</hi> to great paine,</l>
               <l>Shee would not come into his houſe, nor ſcratch his garden-plot,</l>
               <l>But in his Yeard both day and night a kennell there ſhee got:</l>
               <l>At length he tooke her for a Witch, for euery time that hee</l>
               <l>Came there his water for to make, which heretofore went free,</l>
               <l>It now came forkedly with paine, and ſuddenly would ſtop,</l>
               <l>Till that an vlcer like proud fleſh, was in his Yeard begot.</l>
               <l>This Bitches Beldam was a Whelpe, when <hi>Charles</hi> the fift firſt came</l>
               <l>Vnto the ſiege of <hi>Naple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> there, with <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ora</hi> her Dam.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdeo</hi> a ſubtill Hound, that had a Wolfe to Syer,</l>
               <l>Did feed on <hi>Glans</hi> and eate it off, and made it burne like fier.</l>
               <l>This was an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Curre ſome ſay, and grumled as he ran,</l>
               <l>Thence into <hi>England</hi> he was brought, from thence to <hi>France</hi> he came<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>At <hi>Wincheſter</hi> he eate a Gooſe, all wholly ſane the rumpe,</l>
               <l>The which without all feathers cleane, appeared like a ſtumpe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:6"/>But now this while poore <hi>Morbus</hi> head was neuer toucht with greefe,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Alop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce,</hi> that ſhagged Cur, came ſtealing like a theefe</l>
               <l>Behinde, and bit off all his haire, euen to the very skin,</l>
               <l>As if that neuer haire had growne, or on his head had bin.</l>
               <l>A pybalde Prieſt brought vp this Dogge to licke off all his haire,</l>
               <l>For of a Barbers raſor he did euer ſtand in feare.</l>
               <l>Then little <hi>Formica</hi> came in, as buſie as a Bee,</l>
               <l>And all her Beagle Whelpes with her, as nimble limbde as ſhee:</l>
               <l>Theſe for their ſhort and nimble legges, at receipt vſde to lye,</l>
               <l>For that they muſt aduantage take to gaine coape ground thereby;</l>
               <l>Which when they had their prey eſpied, and they poore <hi>Morbus</hi> found,</l>
               <l>That ſore had hunted been of late, and layde him on the ground</l>
               <l>To reſt himſelfe; theſe Whelpes came in, like little Ants a pace,</l>
               <l>Some ran into his necke and breech, ſome bit him by the face,</l>
               <l>And as a man ſhould naked be, roulde in a nettle bed,</l>
               <l>So did they ſtinge and bite his skin, like vnto fier red.</l>
               <l>Then came in <hi>Puſtill</hi> ſpotted red, and on his fore-head light</l>
               <l>Like Tauerne tokens, all beſpread and ſet themſelues in ſight;</l>
               <l>Or like to Starres which in the heauens doe ſhine in froſtie night,</l>
               <l>Some men doe call them <hi>Spaniſh-fleas,</hi> for that they leaue behinde</l>
               <l>Red ſpots or ſtalles where they haue been, as Fleas doe leaue by kinde:</l>
               <l>A Leopard ſure was thought to be, the Syer of this foule Hound,</l>
               <l>For that neere Arden-forreſt he, at <hi>Lyons</hi> firſt was found.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Talpa</hi> ſet on by the reſt, crept vnderneath the skin,</l>
               <l>And as a Mole heaues vp the earth, and ſo runnes deeper in:</l>
               <l>So did this Curre creepe to the skull of ſilly <hi>Morbus</hi> head,</l>
               <l>And foulde the bone, and raiſde it vp, and made therein his bed,</l>
               <l>And lay therein ſo ſecretly, as if he had been dead.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Talpa</hi> was a lazie Curre, and loued to take his reſt,</l>
               <l>Which had a Dam, that <hi>Tophos</hi> hight, as wicked as the beſt:</l>
               <l>This <hi>Tophos</hi> at this time fell lame, and could not goe, nor ſtand,</l>
               <l>And lay in <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> amongſt her kin, vnder a Surgeons hand.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Pollypus</hi> who had to Syer a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ungie <hi>Flemmiſh</hi> Curre,</l>
               <l>Did come and creepe vp <hi>Morbus</hi> noſe, and there ſtucke like a burre,</l>
               <l>Yet could not hide her ſelfe; for why, her taile was ſeene hang downe,</l>
               <l>Much like a Turky-cock, whoſe combe hangs dangling from his crowne,</l>
               <l>And like a Polcats ſtinke, or worſe, this <hi>Pollypus</hi> did make,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Morbus</hi> friends, ſuch as he had, began him to forſake</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:7"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound, bit him behinde the eares,</l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dogge, downe to the skull him teares.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Fiſſure</hi> was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and had two Puppies more,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Dogges,</hi> that plagu'd poore <hi>Morbus</hi> ſore:</l>
               <l>This <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Curre, and ouer vſde to ſcratch,</l>
               <l>And neuer left, till that the bloud his nailes did ouer match.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Scuruy</hi> crept into his ioynts, and made his body lame,</l>
               <l>And raiſde his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his teeth, and brought all out of frame,</l>
               <l>This <hi>Scuruy</hi> had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſometime, in <hi>Rome</hi> not long agoe,</l>
               <l>That dwelt in Cardinall <hi>Corpus</hi> houſe, and reſted in his toe;</l>
               <l>Her name was <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gra,</hi> they ſay, Rich men doe know her well,</l>
               <l>And ſhee made choiſe of <hi>Morbus</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te, therein to bide and dwell.</l>
               <l>Then eating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> came with ſpeed, this was of barbarous kinde,</l>
               <l>But more accurſed Dogge then this, could neuer <hi>Morbus</hi> finde,</l>
               <l>Shee eat his throate and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and made his noſe to fall,</l>
               <l>And ſent out <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> which perfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> his chamber, houſe, and all:</l>
               <l>So that poore <hi>Morbus</hi> had no ſpeech, nor voice to cry or call.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Nodus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Harp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> came, and <hi>Paine</hi> all bred in <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of foure ſuch Dogges you neuer heard, as theſe, all came by chance.</l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>Nodus</hi> bit him by the ſhinnes, and ſometimes on the brow,</l>
               <l>And raiſde vp bunches, knots and bumpes, with aches ioyn'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>now.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Cruſt,</hi> that came of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gies</hi> kinde, both of the Syer and Dam</l>
               <l>All ouer <hi>Morbus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> skin, full ſuddenly he ran,</l>
               <l>And neuer left, till that his crowne he conquered had and wan.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Herpes,</hi> hee with creeping pace, went eating all the way,</l>
               <l>And caſt vp furrowes like a Mole, with feeding night and day,</l>
               <l>And crau'd of <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt,</hi> where he had fed, to hide it if he may.</l>
               <l>At length came <hi>Paine,</hi> that hunts by night, and bit him skin and bone;</l>
               <l>And though he biteth many a man, yet choſe he him alone,</l>
               <l>To feed vpon in bed a nights, that <hi>Morbus</hi> could not ſleepe,</l>
               <l>But tend the feeding of his Hounds, as Shepherds doe their ſheepe.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Furſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> hee, a Bakers Dogge, and bred in <hi>Britaine</hi> Land,</l>
               <l>But yet a man-kinde Curre to feed, and bite men by the hand;</l>
               <l>Did raiſe vp branny ſcales and duſt, vpon poore <hi>Morbus</hi> skin,</l>
               <l>That of a creature wrapt in woe, was none found like to him:</l>
               <l>Yet was he rich in precious ſtones, but not in gold nor fee,</l>
               <l>That longs to Lords of great eſtate, not ſuch a man as hee:</l>
               <l>But yet a Rich Pearle in his eye, a Ruby on his noſe,</l>
               <l>And in his tayle an Emrod faire, and ſo he ſtately go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:26340:7"/>
               <head>THE MANNER OF CVRING THE French Diſeaſe, according to the conſtitution of <hi>diuers Countries.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>NOw liſt we not no more to ſpeake of Dogs, nor yet of Hounds,</l>
               <l>Poor <hi>Morbus</hi> feels the leaſt of them, as deep as deadly wounds:</l>
               <l>And leaue him in his bed poore man, that cannot go nor ſtand,</l>
               <l>Nor ſcarſe alone can feed himſelfe, ſo weake in lim and hand.</l>
               <l>But yet a fained helpe at laſt, a friend of his profeſt,</l>
               <l>And promiſt, if he would be rulde, he ſhould be diſpoſſeſt</l>
               <l>Of all theſe Dogges and ſcuruy Curres, that did him ſo moleſt.</l>
               <l>And therewith brought in <hi>Medicus,</hi> that was a <hi>Florintine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enis, Naples,</hi> and of <hi>Rome,</hi> and euery where ſometime;</l>
               <l>Howbeit, well knowne a Mountebank, that went from towne to towne</l>
               <l>With <hi>Venis</hi>-Treacle, and with Drugges, that he ſould vp and downe:</l>
               <l>With him came <hi>Pharmacus,</hi> High-<hi>Dutch,</hi> a Pothecaries man,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Leech,</hi> a <hi>German</hi> Quackſaluer, that from his Maſter ran,</l>
               <l>For three ſuch knaues, if hel were ſought, more worſe could not be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d:</l>
               <l>Yet in thoſe Countries euery where, ſuch ſtragauants abound.</l>
               <l>And theſe did all with one conſent, him promiſe helpe with ſpeed;</l>
               <l>So he could money purchaſe them, to recompence their meed.</l>
               <l>Which being done, they fell to worke, all like a packe of knaues,</l>
               <l>For many a hundred they had ſent aliue into their graues:</l>
               <l>And therefore knew the way full well, to helpe this craſie man;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Medicus</hi> to countenance all, he was the firſt began,</l>
               <l>And Noynted <hi>Morbus</hi> ouer all, about with Vygoes greaſe,</l>
               <l>And ſweat him in a tubbe, whereby that all his paines ſhould ceaſe.</l>
               <l>What followed next is ſhame to tell, but ſo he brought about,</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Morbus</hi> tongue and gumbes did ſwell, and all his teeth fell out.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Pharmacus</hi> with gliſters, and Horſe-leaches in a glaſſe,</l>
               <l>Began his Muſicke, and applied his Bagpipes to his arſte.</l>
               <l>Yet all this while poore <hi>Morbus</hi> head did neuer take no reſt,</l>
               <l>For day and night his new-made paines, each hower did him moleſt.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Leech</hi> he tooke a wimble vp, and borde him through the skull,</l>
               <l>This wimble he a <hi>Trepan</hi> call'd, and out a peece did pull,</l>
               <l>And powr'd in Kyſt, and made him drinke, <hi>Spruſe</hi>-Beere his belly full,</l>
               <l>Till that they laid him in a trance, and whilſt that did endure,</l>
               <l>They ſtole away, and left report, that he was paſt all cure.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:8"/>Now when all hopes were paſt and gone, and Art no more could try,</l>
               <l>And he growne ſicke and faint, and lookt each hower for to dye;</l>
               <l>He counſelled was to ſeeke a Prieſt, and haue minde of his ſoule,</l>
               <l>Leſt ſudden death ſhould take him hence before his bell could toule:</l>
               <l>The Prieſt was ſent for out of hand, a little poore old man,</l>
               <l>And prayde make haſte, I will (quoth he) make all the haſte I can<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Belike the Prieſt had vnderſtood before of <hi>Morbus</hi> name,</l>
               <l>And would haue poſted off to goe, had it not been for ſhame;</l>
               <l>And more, for being ſpoken to, he may not it denie,</l>
               <l>And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with more ſpeed, before the man ſhould die:</l>
               <l>So when he came and entred in the chamber where he lay,</l>
               <l>And ſaw poore <hi>Morbus</hi> looke on him, and neuer a word did ſay;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ſaid the Prieſt, be anſwered ſoft, <hi>&amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Prieſt was angry at that word, and thought he calde him Iew;</l>
               <l>And would haue gone away in rage, had not ſome for Gods ſake</l>
               <l>Requeſted him to ſtay; for why, he did the ſicke miſtake,</l>
               <l>And tolde him that his throate was ſore, and all his teeth were out,</l>
               <l>He could not ſpeake, and ſtinke perfumde his chamber round about:</l>
               <l>Then did this Prieſt thinke with himſelfe, he ſhould commit great ſin,</l>
               <l>If that the ſacred bleſſed Hoſt he ſhould giue vnto him,</l>
               <l>To ſwallow downe by ſtinking mouth, and throate filde with the <hi>Pox,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He turnde about, and ſecretly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulde out a little box,</l>
               <l>That in his wide gowne ſleeue had hid, and that of purpoſe thought,</l>
               <l>As ſome doe thinke, for in the ſame a Turnep he had brought,</l>
               <l>And priuately cut off a ſlice thereof, and ſomewhat thin,</l>
               <l>And after ceremonies done, the vile Prieſt gaue it him;</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Morbus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oulde it in his mouth, becauſe his throate was rough,</l>
               <l>And through his noſe hee tolde the Prieſt, his God was very tough:</l>
               <l>The Prieſt then bade him ſwallow it downe, though it put him to paine,</l>
               <l>The merit of his owne free-will in heauen ſhould finde a gaine:</l>
               <l>With that poore <hi>Morbus</hi> forſt himſelfe to ſwallow downe the Hoſt,</l>
               <l>And in that doing choakt himſelfe, and ſo gaue vp the ghoſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in pace,</hi> ſaid the Prieſt, ſo reſt thy ſoule in peace,</l>
               <l>For now by death thy ſinnes and paines ſhall heere for euer ceaſe.</l>
               <l>Twas well done, ſaid <hi>Pild-Garlike</hi> then, to eaſe him of his greefe,</l>
               <l>But yet I wiſh a better cure ſhould come for my releefe:</l>
               <l>And for the tale which thou haſt tolde, I like it paſſing well,</l>
               <l>But thou therein haſt been too bold, as now I will thee tell.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:8"/>The <hi>Gonoraea</hi> perhaps thou knoweſt by diuers waies may come,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Alopece</hi> by ſickneſſe long, and <hi>Scorbute</hi> which doth run</l>
               <l>Amongſt the Ioynts and maketh lame, and likewiſe for the <hi>Goute,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The which belongs vnto great Lords, not for to ieſt or floute:</l>
               <l>Tis knowne Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> dyed thereof, and <hi>Lewes</hi> the twelfth of <hi>France;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And many Princes of great ſtate, whom Honor did aduance,</l>
               <l>And had no <hi>Pox</hi> at all men know, therefore who made the ſame</l>
               <l>Did want of matter for to write, or elſe he was too blame.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pild-Garlick</hi> you are much deceiude, and that for want of skill</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pox</hi> is maſter of all griefes, where he may haue his will:</l>
               <l>Who hath the <hi>Skuruy, Alopece,</hi> or running of the <hi>Raynes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Serpigo, Hemrods,</hi> or the <hi>Piles,</hi> or whatſoere breeds paynes.</l>
               <l>If that the <hi>Pox</hi> be there before, he maſter is of all;</l>
               <l>See <hi>Parraſelſus,</hi> which hath writ, of <hi>Poxes</hi> great and ſmall,</l>
               <l>And he will ſay a pockie <hi>Goute,</hi> and dropſies of that kinde,</l>
               <l>And more diſeaſes which ſome men by paynes doe chance to finde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Pox</hi> will breede, and Naturalize by law of Propinquinitie,</l>
               <l>And double all their force and paynes, by neereneſſe of Affinitie.</l>
               <l>Well anſwered then, <hi>Pild-Garlicke</hi> ſaid, thy iudgement likes me well,</l>
               <l>Ile grace thy Booke where ere I goe, as alſo where I dwell.</l>
               <l>But, Honeſt friend, after all this, one thing doth yet remaine,</l>
               <l>To helpe poore <hi>Morbus</hi> in this caſe, and how to cure his paine,</l>
               <l>And kill or poyſon all his Dogges, for ſure there is a way;</l>
               <l>For I my ſelfe haue thriſe bin curde, as thou haſt heard me ſay:</l>
               <l>Yet know I not, for want of skill, in this what courſe to take,</l>
               <l>For diuers I doe ſee doth marre, the cures which others make.</l>
               <l>Maſter <hi>Pild-Garlicke,</hi> I am diſpoſde to ſatisfie your minde:</l>
               <l>I ſee you gentle in your ſpeech, and in correction kinde,</l>
               <l>Where you finde fault, I take it well, but ſome no words can pleaſe,</l>
               <l>I would ſuch men our words diſtaſte, might taſte our <hi>Spaniſh-Fleas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And now, Sir, ſince you me requeſt, and for ſome are abuſde,</l>
               <l>Ile write you Medicens of the beſt, and how they may be vſde,</l>
               <l>And which ſhall cure all griefes thereof, conſeruing your intent,</l>
               <l>If the Diſeaſe be not confinnde, or Nature too much ſpent.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:26340:9"/>
               <head>THE MANNER OF CVRING THE French <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eaſe, according to the conſtitution of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Countries.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>THe <hi>Indians</hi> of the Weſtern parts, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce this Diſeaſe firſt came,</l>
               <l>Doth vſe <hi>Tobacco</hi> diuers wayes, to cure and helpe the ſame:</l>
               <l>They eate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to purge the bloud, and ſternu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation make</l>
               <l>For head ache paynes, and then the ſmoak to draw the rhume they take.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> forty years ago that into <hi>Flanders</hi> came,</l>
               <l>And brought the <hi>Pox,</hi> or got them there, to eaſe them now and than</l>
               <l>Of their ſore pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sena</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake, which into poulder ſmall</l>
               <l>They did reduce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tartar</hi> white, the dose a dram was all,</l>
               <l>Which eu'ry morning they would take, goe where ſoere they will,</l>
               <l>This did them eaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe, the which did vſe it ſtill.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>Portugals,</hi> that came from new found <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth vſe to boyle them <hi>Saſſafras,</hi> to eaſe them of their paine;</l>
               <l>And taking of no other drinke, for this they thinke moſt ſure,</l>
               <l>Saue that each other fourth day, whilſt this drinke doth endure,</l>
               <l>They purge them with <hi>Mecho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>can</hi> and ſo performe the cure.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Italy</hi> the Curteſans, and thoſe of better ſort,</l>
               <l>Doe take the <hi>Chyma</hi>-roote for helpe, as ſome of them report,</l>
               <l>The which with <hi>Salſa,</hi> and nought elſe, a faire decoction make,</l>
               <l>And for their cure while that doth dure, no other drinke they take,</l>
               <l>Saue that ſome <hi>Rubarbe</hi> now and then, they vſe for pleaſures ſake.</l>
               <l>The <hi>French</hi> doth vſe the <hi>Holly-wood,</hi> which from <hi>Domingo</hi> came,</l>
               <l>Which cauſeth vomit, and doth purge with eaſe to euery man,</l>
               <l>And ſince they are moſt cunning in decoctions of all kindes,</l>
               <l>With purging, ſweats, and dyet rules, as beſt ſhall pleaſe their mindes.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> to cure their <hi>Spaniſh-Fleas,</hi> doe make of dyet drinkes,</l>
               <l>Some for to purge, to ſweate, and drie, each man as beſt he thinkes.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> they ſcarce know this griefe, till they abroad doe roame,</l>
               <l>And if they poyſoned be therewith, they heale when they come home.</l>
               <l>If they be ſicke, or Feuor-like, or what diſeaſe doth fall,</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Shamrok</hi> and their <hi>Bonny-Clabb,</hi> is medicen good for all.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Flemmings</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> doe <hi>Lignum vitae</hi> take,</l>
               <l>And with the <hi>Cortex</hi> of the ſame, a drying dyet make:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:9"/>And ſometimes vſe a purging drinke, ſome ſtrong, another ſmall,</l>
               <l>Sometime a drinke of both effects, to drie and purge withall.</l>
               <l>Thus doe we ſee that God hath ſent, a ſalue for eu'ry ſore,</l>
               <l>And eu'ry Country to their kinde, is fit with Medicens ſtore.</l>
               <l>But ſince we meane to make compleate, this worke wee haue begun,</l>
               <l>And leaue the worke of Nature out, and vnto arte to run.</l>
               <l>And leſt that other men ſhould iudge vs ſimple in the ſame,</l>
               <l>Weele ſpeake the truth of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te we know, ſo ſhall we voyd the blame.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Germanes</hi> with their <hi>Spagirike</hi> and <hi>Chymick</hi> Doctors ſay,</l>
               <l>That they in curing of the <hi>Pox,</hi> haue found a better way,</l>
               <l>Then heretofore hath practiſde bin, and how that <hi>Mercury</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is Lord and Patron of the <hi>Pox,</hi> as euery man may try.</l>
               <l>For whereas eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry Planet elſe, in <hi>Mutocoſmos</hi> raignes</l>
               <l>And rules the Heart, the Lungs and Braynes, the Artiers and the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ines.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Mercury</hi> hath no certaine place, but doth vſurpe of all,</l>
               <l>As we doe ſee how that the <hi>Pox,</hi> in eu'ry place doth fall</l>
               <l>About the body of a man, which makes our iudgement ſure,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Mercury</hi> is the Lord of it, ſo <hi>Mercury</hi> makes the cure.</l>
               <l>And therefore ſome take <hi>Argent vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> which <hi>Mercury</hi> they call,</l>
               <l>The which with <hi>Spirits</hi> of <hi>Vitriale,</hi> a <hi>Turpet</hi> makes withall;</l>
               <l>And of the ſame, forme little Pills, with pulpe of Apples roſt,</l>
               <l>And giue ten graines thereof at once, twelue graines muſt be the moſt;</l>
               <l>And oft to drinke hot Poſtell Whaye, that hath decoct therein,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdus Benedictus</hi> toppes, to helpe the Flux, begin.</l>
               <l>Then in the <hi>Intrim</hi> now and then, with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enis Treacle</hi> ſweate,</l>
               <l>And ſee each thing he take be warme, which he ſhall drinke or eate,</l>
               <l>And waſh his mouth with Vineger, that hath Roſe-water mixt,</l>
               <l>That tween his tongue, his teeth and cheeks, there lyes no filth betwixt:</l>
               <l>And giue the pills but till you ſee, the Flux begins to come;</l>
               <l>And keepe him from colde ayer and winde, vntill the Flux be done:</l>
               <l>Then make a dyet drinke which ſhall reuert the matter downe,</l>
               <l>And you ſhall cure as well as the beſt Barber in the Towne:</l>
               <l>Prouided that no <hi>Nodes</hi> remaine, on <hi>Perioſtion</hi> fixt,</l>
               <l>For they are tumors full of paine, by tarterous humors mixt:</l>
               <l>Nor doe not the diſeaſe miſtake, in vſing <hi>Mercury,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For feare Ioynt Aches, or worſe paines, you doe procure thereby;</l>
               <l>Nor ſee that no obſtructions be, or fragments let remaine,</l>
               <l>For then there will a relaps call the <hi>French-man</hi> backe againe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:10"/>And one thing more, obſerue the Moone, at Change or Full begin,</l>
               <l>And purge not in a fixed Signe, if thou wouldſt credit win:</l>
               <l>And for that preparation muſt in all things goe before,</l>
               <l>Seeke to the learn'd Phyſition for, his counſell euermore.</l>
               <l>I haue beene heere too large in ſpeech, I feare I ſhall be ſhent,</l>
               <l>But that a rule I thought to forme, and that was my intent:</l>
               <l>For all theſe <hi>Turpets</hi> which are giuen, muſt worke but one effect,</l>
               <l>Therefore be conſtant in your cure, that Nature be not checkt,</l>
               <l>Which if you doe, he dyes for it; this <hi>Item</hi> take of mee,</l>
               <l>The daintier that the body is, the ſooner dead is he.</l>
               <l>The yellow <hi>Turpets</hi> which are made, with ſpirit of <hi>Vitriall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And gold with <hi>Mercury</hi> conſtant fixt, which ſome iudge beſt of all:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Petr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade by <hi>Phirouant,</hi> which he extols ſo hie,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Mercury,</hi> gold, and yron fixt, which I thinke few doe trie,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Diafortick Mercuries,</hi> and how to vſe the ſame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercurius vitae</hi> and his vſe, that beares ſo great a name:</l>
               <l>The fume or ſmoake of <hi>Synaber</hi> the Vnction for to ſweat;</l>
               <l>Of euery thing ſomewhat is ſpoke, or need of to intreat.</l>
               <l>For heere in briefe I leaue them out, and ſend you to the Booke,</l>
               <l>Where you ſhall finde them eu'ry one, at leaſure if you looke:</l>
               <l>Nor doe I meane in Chirurgery to ſpend heere any time,</l>
               <l>To ſpeake of <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kes</hi> which corrodes the <hi>Buboes</hi> of the groyne:</l>
               <l>Of Poulders, Lotions, and ſuch like, which <hi>Virga</hi> doth requier:</l>
               <l>Of Squirts, and waters for't in vſe, which ſmarts and burnes like fier:</l>
               <l>Of Launcets nor Inciſſion Kniues, nor Candles made of waxe,</l>
               <l>To proabe the ſore, <hi>Caruncula,</hi> with diuers other knackes:</l>
               <l>The laying bare of <hi>Cranium,</hi> the <hi>Nodes</hi> vpon the ſhinnes,</l>
               <l>Then for to raſpe and ſcale the bones, the Surgeons gaine beginnes:</l>
               <l>Ne doe we heere deny ſuch things, when we haue cauſe to vſe them;</l>
               <l>But he that hath no need thereof, were better to refuſe them.</l>
               <l>The laſt are Women-Surgeons, which doe carry dyet drinke,</l>
               <l>And Oyntments in a boxe, to ſmeare their Patients till they ſtinke;</l>
               <l>And will compare with Surgeons all, what ranke ſo ere they bee;</l>
               <l>Againſt Phyſitians ſheele accept, and be as good as hee;</l>
               <l>Shee hath of Medicens which ſhee knowes, we haue no vſe of them,</l>
               <l>Nor neuer will her skill reueale to ſuch vnskilfull men:</l>
               <l>Shee hath a Lady which will beare her out in any thing,</l>
               <l>Sheele ſmell and licke their waters all, which people to her bring:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26340:10"/>And ſhe's the Cunning-woman calde, and where ſome gets a peny,</l>
               <l>Sheele haue a ſhilling from their purſe, if money they haue any:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſſarabacca,</hi> and the ſeeds calde <hi>Cattapuſe</hi> of them;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Stibbium</hi> and the <hi>Colliquint,</hi> and ſome <hi>Eleboris</hi> then:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spurge-Comfits, Aloes,</hi> and a drinke, ſhall women get with childe,</l>
               <l>And ſet a Mayden free, which doubts ſome man hath her beguilde:</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Fucus</hi> and her Blaunching-pots and glaſſes with complection,</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Talcum</hi> and her <hi>Spaude</hi> preparde, all of her owne direction:</l>
               <l>Theſe are the ſecret Medicens, which they hold ſo deare of priſe,</l>
               <l>A Iew did bid her keepe them ſafe, from learned and vnwiſe.</l>
               <l>Ne doe I heere of Ladies ſpeake, nor Gentry in this land,</l>
               <l>Who in their Countries doe great cures, performed by their hand;</l>
               <l>The which in Chriſtian charity, and for no hope of gaine,</l>
               <l>Refuſe no counſell, nor no coſt, nor ſpares for any paine.</l>
               <l>Enough, enough, <hi>Pild-Garlicke</hi> ſaid, tis time that I were gone,</l>
               <l>To ſpeake of Women-Surgeons now, I thinke there's ten for one</l>
               <l>That rationall Surgeons be, but who can it redreſſe;</l>
               <l>The more they threate to put them downe, the more they doe increaſe:</l>
               <l>For ſome are backt by mightie men, and Ladies, as they ſay,</l>
               <l>Therefore to make an end of them, lets now no longer ſtay.</l>
               <l>One word or two, and ſo an end, quoth he that made the Booke,</l>
               <l>Wiſh each good man comes to the hedge, before he leape, to looke:</l>
               <l>And let him not that hath the <hi>Pox,</hi> thinke for to weare it out,</l>
               <l>But firſt to ſeeke for helpe in time, for feare of further doubt.</l>
               <l>Who happens in a Surgeons hand, where Arte and Vertue dwell,</l>
               <l>Such Patients they are bleſt of God, the others liue in hell.</l>
               <l>Giue mee thy Booke <hi>Pild-Garlicke</hi> ſaid, and lend to me thy hand,</l>
               <l>I neuer met a merryer Knaue, in any Realme or Land.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="glossary">
            <pb facs="tcp:26340:11"/>
            <head>THE MEANING OF CER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINE WORDS OR NAMES, which ſeemeth to ſome hard to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand in this Booke.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CVrte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an,</hi> a Whore by licence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veneris,</hi> Lechery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Superbus Publicus,</hi> a common noted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roud man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Gallicus,</hi> the French-Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Ouids</hi> Metam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gonorea gallica,</hi> the ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing of the Rey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s in that Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caruncula,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Excrece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſegr-wing in the Yard of a man, by lying with vncleane women.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bubo venerius,</hi> is a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tch in the Groyn, which commeth by a ſudden ſtopp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the flux of the Reynes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amorons,</hi> are certaine fleſhie excrecenſes, at the beginning like Mulberries, and as they drie like Warts, and grow on the head of a mans Yard</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glans,</hi> is the Acorne or head of a mans Yard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia gallica,</hi> is meant the falling of the haire in this Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spaniſh-Buttons, Puſtills,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Fleas,</hi> are drie Scabbes appearing in the head and forhead, and when they fall away, they leaue red ſtooles be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inde, like Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a-b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Talpa,</hi> is a virulent Diſeaſe, and fouleth the vpper table of the <hi>Cranium</hi> or Scull, and raiſeth vp the bone, as a Mole heaueth vp the earth before him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tophi,</hi> are groſſe humors and viſcon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lying vpon <hi>Cranium</hi> vnder <hi>Petioſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and maketh one part of the head or forhead ſeeme bigger than the other part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perioſtion,</hi> is a skinne that couereth all the bones of the body of man, and groweth to the ſame, and on that the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiſſurae,</hi> are chappes or clifes ſometime happening behinde the eares, the toes, the fundements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scorbutum,</hi> the Scuruie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Canker,</hi> is a venemous eating vlcer, and may be ſister to <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> differing onely in the cure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26340:11"/>
               <hi>Nodus,</hi> are bunches on the brow or ſhin-bones, they differ from <hi>Tophi</hi> in this, that <hi>Tophi</hi> lyeth vnder the <hi>Perioſtion,</hi> and this lyeth vpon it, and therefore moſt painfulleſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cruſt,</hi> is a Scabbe, which in this Diſeaſe runneth all the body ouer, like a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Scall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herpes</hi> and <hi>Serpigoes,</hi> are Tetters and Ring-wormes, ingendred of ſalt-flegme or tumor <hi>Eriſipelas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Formica,</hi> is a pricking or ſtinging in the skinne, as if a man were bitten with Ants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Furfur,</hi> is a duſt like vnto Branne, ingendred of vapoures breathing out of the body, and drying on the skinne, and after falleth off in ſcales.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hemrods,</hi> are a painfull Diſeaſe, breaking out about the Fundement from the <hi>Hemrode</hi> veines.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>
               <hi>THE AVTHOVRS WHICH</hi> haue written of this Diſeaſe are diuers and many, neither need I to trouble my ſelfe with ſearching the multitude of them: ſome for the Names, Nature, and Medicaments needfull, I follow.</head>
            <p>DOctor Lowe, <hi>Scotchman, in his Booke</hi> De morbo Hiſpanico.</p>
            <p>Philip Hermanus, <hi>vpon</hi> Paracelſus, <hi>in his Booke</hi> De Morbus gallico, <hi>and Doctor</hi> Monardus <hi>of Ciuil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Method of Phyſicke, <hi>by</hi> Philip Barrow.</p>
            <p>Penotus <hi>a French-man, in his Booke</hi> De Medicamentis Chymicis, <hi>and his</hi> Denarium.</p>
            <p>Crollius <hi>in his Booke</hi> Baſillica Medicamentis.</p>
            <p>Quercitanus <hi>in his</hi> Pharmacopaea.</p>
            <p>Phyrouant <hi>in his Booke of</hi> Secrets.</p>
            <p>Tyrocinium Chymicum.</p>
            <p>Iohannes de Vigo.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
